Guide to the John Emory Bryant Papers, 1851-1955 and undated RL.00167
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Emory Bryant papers
1851-1955 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bryant, John Emory, 1836-1900
RL.00167
11 Linear Feet
Born in Union, Maine, John Emory Bryant (1836-1900) was an abolitionist, teacher, Union officer with the 8th Maine Volunteers, agent of the Freedmen's Bureau, newspaper editor and publisher, lawyer, and Republican politician in Georgia. The collection includes letters, journals, scrapbooks, writings, speeches, and printed materials related to the lives of John Emory Bryant (JEB), his wife Emma Spaulding Bryant, their daughter Emma Alice Zeller and her husband Julius Zeller and their descendants, and William Anderson Pledger who was a Republican contemporary of JEB. The bulk of the collection falls into four main divisions: the early years in Maine (1851-1860), during the American-Civil War (1861-1865), during Reconstruction in Georgia, and the later years in New York (1888-1900). Some of the materials are not original and are copies or typescripts. Of note are materials regarding Georgian Republican politics; conditions for Radical Republicans and African-Americans during Reconstruction, including correspondence with Henry McNeal Turner; historical views about the differences between the North and the South; Ku Klux Klan activity in Georgia, Florida, and Alabama; and a particularly passionate exchange between Emma Spaulding Bryant and her husband regarding her visits to a doctor about "uterine difficulties" (these 10 letters from Emma Bryant have been digitized and are available online).
Arrangement
Arranged according to the following series: Correspondence; Legal and Financial; Writings, Journals, and Scrapbooks; Printed Materials and Ephemera; William Anderson Pledger.
Collection Overview
The collection includes letters, journals, scrapbooks, writings, speeches, and printed materials related to the lives of John Emory Bryant (JEB), his wife Emma Spaulding Bryant, their daughter Emma Alice Zeller and her husband Julius Zeller and their descendants, and William Anderson Pledger who was a Republican contemporary of JEB. The bulk of the collection falls into four main divisions: the early years in Maine (1851-1860), during the American-Civil War (1861-1865), during Reconstruction in Georgia and after (1865-1887), and the later years in New York (1888-1900). Some of the materials are not original and are copies or typescripts. Of note are materials regarding Georgian Republican politics; conditions for Radical Republicans and African-Americans during Reconstruction, including correspondence with Henry McNeal Turner; historical views about the differences between the North and the South; Ku Klux Klan activity in Georgia, Florida, and Alabama; and a particularly passionate exchange between Emma Spaulding Bryant and her husband regarding her visits to a doctor about "uterine difficulties." These 10 letters from Emma Bryant have been digitized and are available online at: https://library.duke.edu/specialcollections/scriptorium/bryant/
Biographical Note
Born in Union, Maine, John Emory Bryant (1836-1900) was an abolitionist, teacher, Union officer with the 8th Maine Volunteers, agent of the Freedmen's Bureau, newspaper editor and publisher, lawyer, and Republican politician in Georgia. During the American Civil War Bryant served in the Department of the South, in the Sea Island of Georgia and South Carolina. There he worked with General Rufus Saxton and commanded African-American troops, leading raids to free slaves from nearby plantations. In 1864 Bryant married Emma Frances Spaulding (1844-1901), who was born in Buckfield, Maine. They had two children together, a son who died in infancy and a daughter Alice. After the war, Bryant returned to Georgia and was heavily involved in Georgian Republican politics, serving as a congressman for one term and as state party chairman from 1876-1880. Bryant was involved in many organizations including the Georgia Equal Rights Association, the Methodist Episcopal Church, the Southern Advance Association, and the Sons of Temperance.
William Anderson Pledger (1852-1904) was an editor of the Atlanta Blade newspaper, teacher, prominent Black Republican politician in Georgia, and friend of John Emory Bryant. In 1880 Pledger was elected chairman of the Republican state committee in Georgia, the first Black man to serve in that office. Pledger helped organize the Afro-American League (which later became the Afro-American Council) in 1890 in Chicago and served as vice president in 1898.
Biographical note adapted from American National Biography:
https://doi-org.proxy.lib.duke.edu/10.1093/anb/9780198606697.article.0401189
https://doi.org/10.1093/anb/9780198606697.article.1500551
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The John Emory Bryant Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1968 and 2002.
Online items
Selected items from this collection have been digitized and are available in the Emma Spaulding Bryant Letters online collection.
Scrapbooks; Black-and-white photographs; African Americans -- Georgia; Freedmen -- Georgia; Temperance -- United States; African Americans -- Politics and government -- Georgia; Georgia -- History -- 1865-; South Carolina -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- Georgia; Albumen prints; American Civil War (1861-1865); Women's Health -- 19th century; Diaries; Temperance -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Bryant family; Bryant, John Emory, 1836-1900; Pledger, William Anderson; Methodist Episcopal Church -- Georgia; Turner, Henry McNeal, 1834-1915; Republican Party (Ga.); United States. Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands; United States. Army. Maine Infantry Regiment, 8th (1861-1866); Bryant, Emma Spaulding, 1844-1901; Georgia Equal Rights and Educational Association; Ku Klux Klan (19th cent.); Saxton, Rufus, 1824-1908
- Correspondence, 1851-1916 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of the letters cover the years before the American Civil War when John Emory Bryant (JEB) and Emma Spaulding were in Maine, during the Civil War when JEB was at Port Royal and Hilton Head, S.C., during Reconstruction in Georgia (1865-1887), and the remaining years in New York (1888-1900). The letters document JEB's life as a soldier, his courtship and relationship with his wife Emma Spaulding, his involvement in the Republican Party, temperance organizations, the Freedman's Bureau, and the Methodist Episcopal Church, as well as his relationships with other politicians such as President Ulysses S. Grant, James Atkins, Governor Rufus Bullock, and Foster Blodgett, including prominent African-American politicians of the time such as Henry McNeal Turner and William Anderson Pledger.
  Most of the letters during the Civil War were written between JEB and Emma Spaulding, whom he knew before the war when she was his student at Kent's Hill. The letters describe their courtship, their social lives, and also the conditions during the war. Some of the letters during this period are official orders from officers in the Union Army, including General Rufus Saxton, with whom JEB would continue to work after the war in the Freedman's Bureau.
  There are also three volumes from the Confederate Army in Georgia that include official correspondence of the Camps of Instruction for Conscripts in the 7th and 8th Congressional Districts of Georgia and correspondence from the headquarters of Brigadier General Raleigh Edward Colston's Brigade at Fort Bartow, Georgia. It is unclear how these Confederate volumes ended up with Bryant, though it is speculated that they were found by Christopher C. Richardson of the 11th Maine Volunteers who was stationed at Griffin, Georgia, for a short time in 1865. These volumes also include added notes, correspondence, and clippings from John Emory Bryant, Captain Christopher C. Richardson (business partner of Bryant who was later killed by a political opponent), and a Black clerk named G. B. Snowden who worked at Bryant and Richardson's law firm. These volumes cover the years 1863-1868 and include information about the Freedmen's Bureau at Augusta, conditions for Black people in Augusta following the Civil War, and the Republican Club of Augusta. Bryant also pasted in letters from General Rufus Saxton, 1865.
  There are a series of letters from Henry McNeal Turner (1834-1915) during April, 1866. Turner was a Black Republican leader, legislator, preacher, and Post Master of Augusta, Georgia. Turner became a bishop in the African Methodist Church, 1880-1892. His letters to Bryant describe his political activity and aspirations. On April 6th, amidst the grave illness of his wife and the death of one of his children, he writes, "Please let me have the last law passed by the Georgia legislature, granting the colored people all the protection given to the white. They claim here that Georgia has granted every right, except voting."
  There are several letters throughout the collection that document conditions for Black people in Georgia. While serving picket duty on a plantation in Beaufort, S. C., on September 8th, 1862, Bryant describes attending a prayer meeting, where he heard the sermon and the call and response singing. In one letter written in 1869, African-American minister Charles R. Edwardes introduces the Colored Men of the Mechanics and Laboring Men Association to JEB. Edwardes explains how the organization wanted to help freed people buy land and homes. In 1868, Mr. P. Joiner writes to JEB reporting the shooting of a Black man by White democrats near Albany, Georgia. The White mob then continued on a rampage through the countryside, warning African Americans that it was "their country and they was going to rule it."
  Much of the correspondence after the Civil War pertains to JEB's political career, aspirations, and struggles. He was a strong proponent of civil rights for African-American men, a cause that he fought for throughout his life, to the chagrin of many of his political opponents. Over the years he was embroiled in several conflicts, and at least three times charges were brought against him for corruption, charges that were eventually dropped. The letters document the different political cliques that he belonged to and fell out of favor with, his participation in the downfall of Governor Rufus Bullock, the jockeying for governmental jobs, and his attempts and failures to maintain financially viable Republican newspapers.
  The correspondence between JEB and his wife Emma Spaulding Bryant documents their personal, professional, and political lives, much of which was spent living apart due to the instability of JEB's employment and the hostile living conditions for Radical Republicans in the South. Emma Bryant describes family life, financial hardship and her efforts to support herself, her interest in painting and drawing, education, and her religious and political beliefs. A particularly difficult moment between Emma and John is captured in Emma's letters from July and August of 1873. These letters shed light on women's health in the 19th century and the relationships between spouses when making medical decisions. The letters recount Emma's activities during that summer when she and her daughter Alice, were visiting relatives in Illinois and Ohio while JEB tended to his political affairs in Georgia. Emma visited a doctor for "uterine difficulties." In response to "insane" and "mad" telegrams sent by her husband, she defends her choice to see a doctor. She describes the treatment that she receives from the doctor, how she wishes to be treated with equality from her husband, and how insulted she is by the accusations of infidelity being sent to her by JEB. On August 7 she describes her husband's behavior and her response, "taunts me with leaving my baby for a few days in care of her Grandma and aunty! Morally raises the lash over me and says 'now will you obey? Will you be my inferior, my obedient child?' To him I answer Never – I will be your true loving wife, your companion and equal in every and the fullest sense – the mother of your children – nothing less and nothing else…" She also writes that she had no choice but to see a male doctor, "His manner of treatment was perfectly delicate and such as all women afflicted with such disease and wishing to recover must receive at the hands of some male physician until there are sufficient educated female physicians to supersede the males." The Bryants soon overcame this dispute. This portion of the Bryants' letters have been digitized and transcribed and can be found here: https://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/scriptorium/bryant/
  - Correspondence, 1851-1958 (Box 1, Oversize-folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1858-1859 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1860-1861 (Box 1)
  - Sons of Temperance, State of Maine, 1860-1861 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1861; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (typed transcripts), 1861-1863 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1862; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1863; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (typed transcripts), 1863-1864 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1864-1865 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1866 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1866-1867 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1867; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1868 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1868-1869; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1869 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1870; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1871; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1871; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1872; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1873 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1873-1874 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1874 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1874 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1876; 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1877; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1877 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1878; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1879; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1880; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1880-1882 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1882 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1883 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1883-1884 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1884 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1885 (Box 4)
  - American Institute of Civics, 1886 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1886; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1887; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1888 (Box 5)
  - Letter to General Benjamin Harrison, 1889 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1889; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1889 January 2 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1889 February 8; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1889 April 25 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1890 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1891; 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1891 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1892-1894 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1895; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1895-1896; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1896 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1896-1897 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1897 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1897; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1898; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1899; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1899-1900 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1900; 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1907 and undated (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (photocopies), 1860-1900 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (photocopies), 1859-1916) (Box 8)
  - Address book, undated (Box 8)
  - John Emory Bryant's letter book, 1876-1877; 1 volume (Box 9)
    Correspondence of JEB and his assistant Volney Spalding. It begins with the campaign of Bryant for Congress in 1876 and his fight with James Atkins. Covers the founding of the Georgia Republican in Atlanta and the fight against the ratification of the new state constitiution in 1877. Refernece is also made to the location of the state capitol at Atlanta and the Homestead Act of 1868.
  - John Emory Bryant's letter book, 1888-1891; 1 volume (Box 9)
    A record of JEB's business ventures in New York City, as well as a number of letters on the "Southern Problem."
  - John Emory Bryant's letter book (typescript), 1876-1877 (Box 9)
    Typed by R.B. Zeller, 1955
  - C.S.A. Army letter book for conscription and letter book of John Emory Bryant, Freedman's Bureau, Augusta, Georgia, 1863-1865 (Box 11)
    Contains copies of official correspondence of the Camps of Instruction for Conscripts in the 8th Congressional District of Georgia. The volume contains details on conscript organization, exemptions, substitutes, health, and personnel. Macon and Decatur, Georgia, contained, respectively, Camps Cooper and Randolph for receiving these troops. Also in this letter book, one year later, JEB began his own letter book for the Freedmen's Bureau at Augusta, where he was serving under General Saxton. The correspondence, largely telegraphic describes conditions for foremerly enslaved Black people who were arriving in Augusta. Also documents JEB's attempt to establish a branch bureau at Hamburg, S.C., under command of Black officers and men from the 33rd U.S. Volunteers.
  - C.S.A. Army book for conscription, 1863-1864 (Box 11)
    Letter book of the commandant of conscription in the 7th Congressional District of Georgia, centering in Macon and Griffin, Georgia. In this book JEB pasted the letters of General Rufus Saxton, 1865, and clippings from the Loyal Georgian, 1866.
  - Colsten's Brigade letter book, 1864-1868 (Box 11)
    From the headquarters of Brigadier General Raleigh Edward Colston's Brigade at Fort Bartow, Georgia, where he held a command in the defense of the Savannah River. The correspondence noted is official. JEB's friend and business partner, Captain Christopher C. Richardson of the 12th Maine Volunteers, added to this volume lists of Confederates taking the amnesty oath in 1865 in Brooks, Valdosta, Echols, and Lowndes counties, Georgia. These are followed by memoranda from the law office of Richardson and Bryant in Augusta. A Black clerk who work in the law office named G. B. Snowden kept minutes in this book of the Republican Club of Augusta, Georgia, March 25-September 11, 1868.
  - Colsten's Brigade Amnesty Lists (transcripts typed by Raymond Bryant Zeller), 1940 (Box 8)
- Legal and Financial, 1864-1909; 2
  Papers relating to John Emory Bryant's roles as lawyer, politician, publisher, and real estate agent. Includes fundraising records for organizations such as the Southern Advance Association, Marietta Street Methodist Episcopal Church in Atlanta, and Grant Memorial University. Also includes an incomplete deposition describing violent and murderous Ku Klux Klan activity in Alabama, Florida, and Georgia during the early 1870s. Named African-American victims of the KKK are: Edward Thompson and his wife in Florida; Boss Fullard, Gamble Wright, and John Askie in Dublin, Georgia; and George Daymond in Montgomery County, Georgia. Leaders and members of the Klan are named as well as their relationships to elected and governmental officials.
  - Certificates (photocopies), 1864-1874 (Box 12)
  - Receipts, statements, invoices, 1864-1891 (Box 12)
  - Civil War documents (photo copies), 1864-1905 (Box 12)
  - Legal papers, 1866-1881 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous account books, 1868-1900 (Box 12)
  - Deposition describing Ku Klux Klan activity in Alabama, Florida, and Georgia, 1870s (Box 12)
  - Republican Party fundraising account book, 1879-1884 (Box 12)
  - Atlanta Republican Publishing Company account book, 1879-1886 (Box 12)
  - Southern Advance Association account books, 1880-1886 (Box 12)
  - Marietta Street Methodist Episcopal Church, Atlanta, Georgia account books, 1885-1890 (Box 12)
  - Grant Memorial University account book, 1886 (Box 12)
  - The Record Publishing Co. account book, 1896-1897 (Box 12)
  - Documents concerning John Emory Bryant's death, 1900-1909 (Box 12)
  - Mt. Vernon Suburban Land Co. account book, 1896-1897 (Box 13)
  - First National Bank of Staton Island check book, 1891 (Box 13)
  - Ship account book, 1894 (Box 13)
  - Account book, 1891-1894 (Box 13)
  - Salary book, 1873-1875 (Box 14)
  - Ledger book, 1889-1891 (Box 14)
- Writings, Journals, Scrapbooks, 1853-1950s; 3
  Various personal and professional writings, clippings, pamphlets, and speeches created and collected by the Bryants and Zellers. Includes early speeches made by JEB at the Wesleyan Seminary at Kent's Hill, Maine, showing his early thoughts on temperance, slavery, and women. The series also includes writings and clippings pertaining to political conventions (including the Freedmen's convention of Georgia in 1866), historical views of the differences between the North and South that were being shaped during Reconstruction, and JEB's shift in focus from educating Black people to educating the Southern White working-class people. There are also diaries by Emma Spaulding Bryant, scrapbooks by Alice Zeller and her husband Julius Zeller, and a biography written by Alice Zeller about her parents (John and Emma). Some of the materials are not original and are typescripts and photocopies.
  - Miscellaneous papers, letters, and excerpts by and about John Emory Bryant, 1853-1982 (Box 15)
    Copied by Raymond Bryant Zeller in the 1950s and compiled by Josephine Zeller Megehee in 1982. Includes biography of JEB from "Leslies History of the Republican Party," excerpts from "Maine in the War for the Union," letter from Miriam Zeller Gross to RBZ (her brother), letters written to Gen. O. O. Howard, "Facts concerned with the Ballot for the Negro" as told to John Emory Bryant's daughter, Emma, speeches given at Proceedings of the Freedmans Convention of Georgia, speech at Georgia Convention of Equal Rights, minutes of the Republican Club, letters from letter book (1876), letters to Savannah, Georgia, excerpts from the "History of the State of Georgia."
  - Handwritten and typed copies of John Emory Bryant's journals 1, 3, and 5, 1853-1859 (Box 15)
    Copied by Raymond Bryant Zeller in the 1950s
  - Typed copy of John Emory Bryant's journal 3, 1854-1855 (Box 15)
    Typed by Raymond Bryant Zeller in the 1950s
  - Typed copy of John Emory Bryant's journal 5, 1858-1859 (Box 15)
  - Photocopy and typed transcript of John and Emma Bryants' diary, 1900 (Box 15)
  - Photocopy of Emma Bryant's diary, 1900 (Box 15)
  - Emma Bryant's journal, 1866 (Box 15)
  - Photocopy of Emma Bryant's sketchbook, 1887-1893 (Box 15)
  - "Day to Day Life and Thoughts of John Emory Bryant" written by Raymond Bryant Zeller, 1950s (Box 15)
  - Writings, 1852-1864 (Box 15)
    Chiefly written at the Wesleyan Seminary at Kent's Hill, Maine; the 1864 papers at Buckfield, Maine. Speeches and reports written about various topics including intemperance, slavery, war, patriotism, and the influence of women, perhaps meant to present at debates.
  - Writings, 1866 (Box 15)
    Includes two typed copies of "Proceedings of the Freedmen's Convention of Georgia Assembled at Augusta, January 10th, 1866," handwritten transcript of a speech given to the Georgia Equal Rights Association on January 13, 1866, two typed copies of "Proceeding of the Council of the Georgia Equal Rights Association Assembled at Augusta, Georgia, April 5th, 1866."
  - Writings, 1867-1869 (Box 15)
    Includes two copies of the "Constitution of the State Association of the National Union Association," "The Georgia Educational Movement," signed pledge (perhaps for the Union League of America), speech fragment regarding the governors ability to appoint election managers, and a speech given to the chairman and members of the Republican State Central Committee in which Bryant says that he is resigning from the committee and explains his involvement in politics in Georgia.
  - Writings, 1868-1886 (Box 15)